Finding Aid for Wooster Woodruff Beman papers, 1865-1938
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Wooster Woodruff Beman papers 1865-1938 1878-1922
Beman, Wooster Woodruff, 1850-1922.
0.4 linear feet.
85735 Aa 2
Instructor at Kalamazoo College, later professor of mathematics at the University of Michigan; correspondence, mathematical papers; and miscellaneous topical files.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Helen E. Beman (donor no. 866 ) and came to the library in different accessions, 1936-1945; other papers were transferred from the University of Michigan Library (donor no. 1298 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Wooster Woodruff Beman was born May 28, 1850, in Southington, Conn. He attended school in Valparaiso, Ind., and entered the University of Michigan in 1866, receiving his B.A. degree in 1870. After teaching for a year at Kalamazoo College as instructor in Greek and mathematics, he returned to the University of Michigan as an instructor while also working for his master's degree, which he received in 1873. In 1874, he became assistant professor, in 1882 associate professor, and in 1887 full professor.
In addition to his teaching, Beman wrote books and articles on the history and teaching of elementary mathematics. Among his works are "Nature and Meaning of Numbers" (from the German), and "Continuity and Irrational Numbers." He was the joint author, with D. E. Smith, of "Plane and Solid Geometry," "Higher Arithmetic," "New Plane and Solid Geometry," "Elements of Algebra," "Academic Algebra," translations of "Famous Problems of Elementary Geometry," and "A Brief History of Mathematics."
Beman died on January 1, 1922.
The Beman collection includes correspondence concerning in part general University activities and specifically relating to the University of Michigan Department of Mathematics. Some of his correspondents include Marion L. Burton, Thomas M. Cooley, Edgar J. Goodspeed, William R. Harper, William J. Hussey, Harry B. Hutchins, Volney M. Spalding, William W. Campbell, Arthur G. Hall, E. R. Hedrick, and W. F. Osgood. In the collection, there are also miscellaneous mathematical papers; biographical sketches of James B. Angell, Edward Olney, and Volney M. Spalding; religious addresses; papers (1885-1898) relating to gambling, prostitution, and selling liquor on Sunday in Ann Arbor, Michigan, memoranda on various trips, and a memorial on his death.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Beman, Wooster Woodruff, 1850-1922.; Mathematics.; Prostitution--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Mathematics.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Beman, Wooster Woodruff, 1850-1922.
Contributors:
Burton, Marion Le Roy, 1874-1925.; Campbell, William Wallace, 1862-; Cooley, Thomas McIntyre, 1824-1898.; Goodspeed, Edgar Johnson, 1871-1962.; Hall, Arthur Graham, 1865-1925.; Harper, William Rainey, 1856-1906.; Hedrick, E. R. (Earle Raymond), 1876-1943.; Hussey, William Joseph, 1862-1926.; Hutchins, Harry B. (Harry Burns), 1847-1930.; Osgood, William Fogg, 1864-1943.; Spalding, Volney Morgan, 1849-1918.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence, 1878-1922
  - 1878-1888 (Box 1)
  - 1889-1891 (Box 1)
  - 1892-1897 (Box 1)
  - 1898-1906 (Box 1)
  - 1907-1913 (Box 1)
  - 1914-1922 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Walter W. Campbell, 1892-1900 (Box 1)
  - Arthur G. Hall, 1901-1903 (Box 1)
  - Earle R. Hedrick
    - 1896-1900 (Box 1)
    - 1901-1906 (Box 1)
  - William J. Hussey, 1898-1903 (Box 1)
  - W.F. Osgood, 1900 (Box 1)
  - Volney Spalding (and Effie Spalding), 1893-1918 (Box 1)
    (also biographical information about Spalding)
- Mathematical Papers
  - Extract from Cesaro's Analisi Algebrica (Box 1)
  - Irrational Numbers (Box 1)
  - Petersen's Forelaesninger over Funktion's Theori (Box 1)
  - Saggio (Box 1)
  - Unidentified (Box 1)
- Ann Arbor
  - Petitions and surveillance reports documenting various vice in the city, 1885 and 1898 (Box 1)
    (mainly violations of the laws pertaining to saloons, but also gambling and prostitution)
  - Ann Arbor Charter Commission, 1920 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  - Booklists (Box 1)
  - Notes of visits to Johns Hopkins and Rochester University, 1882 (Box 1)
  - Memorials to W.W. Beman, 1922 (Box 1)
  - Memorials/eulogies to colleagues by W.W. Beman (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan Math Club minutes, 1887-1889 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Clippings (Box 1)
  - Photographs: portraits (Box 1)